[Music]
a poor diet now outranks smoking as the
leading cause of death on the planet as
well specifically in the United States
in the US the number one killer of
Americans is the American diet so if
diet is Humanity's number one killer
then obviously it's the number one thing
to him medical school right sadly
medical students around the world are
poorly trained in nutrition it's not
that medical students aren't interested
in learning about it medical schools
just aren't teaching it without a solid
foundation of clinical nutrition
Knowledge and Skills Physicians
worldwide are generally not equipped to
even begin to have an informed
conversation about nutrition with their
patients how bad is it one study
assessing the clinical nutrition
knowledge of medical doctors found the
majority got
70% of the questions wrong and there
were multiple choice questions so they
should have gotten about a fifth right
just by chance and the wrong answers
were not limited to difficult or
demanding questions for example less
than half could guess how many calories
are in fat carbs and protein only one in
10 knew the recommended protein intake
and only about one and three knew what a
healthy BMI was I mean this is like
super basic nutrition knowledge and
what's worse not only did the majority
of medical doctors get a failing grade
but 30% of those who failed had a high
self-perception of their clinical
nutrition expertise meaning not only
were they clueless about nutrition they
were also clueless that they were
clueless about Nutrition a particularly
bad combination given that doctors are
trusted and influential sources of
healthy eating advice for those majority
of consumers who get information from
their personal healthc care professional
78% indicate making a change in their
eating habits as a result of those
conversations so if everything the
doctor knows they read in some checkout
aisle magazine that's what the patients
are going to be following only a quarter
of doctor surveyed correctly identified
the American Heart association's
recommended number of fruit and
vegetable servings per day and fewer
still were aware of the recommended
daily added sugar l
so how are they going to counsel
patients on it yet again of the doctors
who perceive themselves as having high
nutrition knowledge
93% couldn't answer those two basic
multiple choice
questions a Physicians with no genuine
expertise in say brain surgery are
neither likely to broadcast detail
opinions on that topic nor have their
quote unquote expert opinion solicited
by media and most topical domains in
medicine enjoy such respect we defer
expert opinion and commentary to actual
experts not so with nutrition where the
common knowledge that Physicians are
generally ill trained in this area is
conjoined to routine invitations to
Physicians for their expert opinions on
the matter all too many are willing to
provide their opinions absent any basis
for actual expertise or Worse made on
the basis of bias and personal
preference sometimes directly Tethered
to personal gain such as diet book sales
that's one of the reasons all the
proceeds I receive from my books are
donated directly to charity I don't even
want the appearance of any conflicts of
interest in a culture that routinely
fails to distinguish expertise from Mere
opinion or personal anecdote we
Physicians should be doing all we can to
establish relevant barriers to entry for
expert opinion on diet and nutrition as
in all other matters of genuine medical
significance I mean we're not talking
celebrity gossip lives are at stake and
there are entire Industries devoted to
marketing messages that may conspire
directly against well-informed medical
advice in this
area medical education must be brought
up to date for Physicians to be ill
trained in the very area most impactful
on the rate of premature death at the
population level is an absurd
The Human Condition that mission cannot
be fulfilled if diet is
neglected maybe one place to start is
for Physicians and Healthcare
organizations to collectively begin to
emphasize their seriousness about
nutrition and Healthcare by practicing
what they at least should be preaching
is it appropriate to serve pizza and
soft drinks at a resident conference
while boning the high prevalence of
obesity encouraging patients to eat
healthier a similar poor example exists
in medical conferences
including National meetings where some
morning sessions are accompanied by
foods such as donuts and sausage
[Music]